A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Policy Office, Records, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Policy Office, Records 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009)
The Library of Virginia
44690 and 44701
60.96 cu. ft. (174 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Office of the Governor, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 E. Broad Street, Richmond, Virginia, 23219, accession 44690 transferred on 14 January 2010.
Historical Information
The Policy Office is a division of the Office of the Governor in the Executive Branch of Virginia state government. During Governor Tim Kaine's administration, the Policy Office was responsible for planning and implementing the Governor's policy initiatives, including proposed legislation, as well as overseeing the Administration's response to legislation and initiatives proposed by legislators and other interested parties, managing the Governor's Office review of regulations and developing and issuing executive orders and executive directors. On 11 January 2006, Governor-elect Kaine named Brian Sheppard, then Lt. Governor Kaine's chief of staff, to serve as Policy Director. The Policy Director was assisted in his responsibilities by a Legislative Director/Deputy Policy Director (William L. Murray, January 2006-May 2007; Suzette Denslow, May 2007-January 2009; and Barbara Reese, January 2009-January 2010), Senior Advisor (Mark E. Rubin) and Policy Staff (Steven Gould, 2006-2007; Felix Safro-Katanka, Jr., 2006-2007; Gena Boyle, January 2006-December 2009; Maribel Ramos, 2006-2007; Joyce Walton; Jennie Moline, 2006-2009; Hayes Framme, 2006-2008; Marc Cheatham; and Megan Root).
Scope and Content
The Policy Office Records of Governor Timothy M. Kaine are housed in 174 boxes. The collection is arranged into five (5) series. Series have been designated for: I. Decision Briefs; II. Regulations; III. Legislative Files; IV. Executive Orders and Directives; and V. Policy Analyst Files. These records include agendas, decision briefs, correspondence, memorandums, legislative files, briefing books, meeting notes, subject files, reports, talking points and regulations. These records document the legislative and policy priorities of the Kaine administration (2006-2010). This collection also includes records from Governor Mark Warner's administration (2002-2006).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Decision Briefs, 2005-2010
II. Regulations, 2003-2010
III. Legislative Files, 2006-2009
IV. Executive Orders and Directives, 2006-2010
V. Policy Analyst Files, 2002-2009
Related Material
OFFICE OF THE GOVERNOR-TIM KAINE
A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine Administration Electronic Files, Email, 2002-2010 (bulk 2006-2009). This collection documents the email of the Kaine Administration (2006-2010). The Policy Office Electronic Files series documents the electronic communication of the Policy Office of the Kaine Administration. This series contains 23308 emails in 8 subseries. Subseries have been designated for A. Steven P. Gould Email; B. Suzette Denslow Email; C. Felix Sarfo-Kantanka Email; D. Gena Boyle Email; E. Jennie Moline Email; F. Maribel Ramos Email; G. Megan Root Email; and H. Barbara Reese Email. There are 300 privacy protected and confidential emails in this series that are restricted from public access for 75 years per Code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Types of restricted information may include, but are not limited to: attorney-client communications, and records containing personal/personnel information. The PST file for Brian Shepard, Policy Director, was empty. However, email messages sent by Shepard may be found in the email files of other members of the Kaine Administration (Executive Office, Policy Office, etc.). The Library of Virginia Email Project - Governor Tim Kaine Portal provides access to the Kaine email collection and includes guides to other Kaine administration records.
The Governor Tim Kaine Administration Web Archive Collection, 2006-2010 contains archived versions of websites for the Governor's Office, his initiative sites, and the sites of his cabinet secretaries. Also included are the related sites for the First Lady (Anne Holton), as well as the Lt. Governor (Bill Bolling), and Attorney General (Bob McDonnell and William C. Mims), two statewide officials elected in the same cycle as Governor Kaine.
The Timothy M. Kaine Administration (2006-2010) Cabinet Weekly Reports Digital Collection contains the weekly reports submitted to the Governor and Chief of Staff by the Governor's Cabinet, including the Secretaries of Administration (Viola Baskerville), Agriculture and Forestry (Robert S. Bloxom), Commerce and Trade (Patrick O. Gottschalk), Commonwealth (Daniel C. LeBlanc, Jan-Mar. 2006 and Katherine K. Hanley (Mar. 2006-2010), Education (Dr. Thomas R. Morris), Finance (Jody Wagner, 2006-2008 and Richard D. Brown, 2008-2010), Health and Human Resources (Marilyn Tavenner), Natural Resources (Preston Bryant), Public Safety (John W. Marshall), Technology (Aneesh Chopra, 2006-2009 and Leonard M. Pomata, 2009-2010), and Transportation (Pierce Homer). Also included are reports by the Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness (Robert Crouch), Office of Constituent Services (Marc Cheatham, 2006-2007 and Amber Amato, 2007-2010), Press Office, Policy Office and Virginia Liaison Office. Reports were submitted each Thursday and placed in a binder for the Governor that he took with him at the end of the day on Friday. A second copy of the report was made for the Chief of Staff. The level of detail varied for each cabinet officer and items of importance were highlighted by staff for the Governor. Each report contains information on legislation, Governor's initiatives/special projects, agency matters/operations, events/agency visits, audits/investigations/compliance, stakeholder issues and pending decisions. Governor Kaine wrote handwritten notes and/or marked-up some reports with post-it notes and requested follow up information from the person submitting the report. Those questions and answers are included in this series. This series provides a weekly account of the issues and policy decisions of the Kaine Administration.
The Executive Orders Digital Collection includes 110 executive orders and 9 executive directives issued by Governor Kaine.
A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Governor, Records, 2005-2009. The Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Governor, Records are housed in 45 boxes. The collection is arranged into three (3) series. Series have been designated for: I. Weekly Status Reports; II. State Budget Files; and III. Briefing Binders and Reports. These records include agreements, briefing books, reports, correspondence, memorandums, budget documents, agendas, handouts, invitations, talking points, and speeches. This collection contains the weekly reports, briefing books and budgetary records of Governor Kaine (2006-2010).
A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Chief of Staff, Records, 2006-2009. The Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Chief of Staff, Records are housed in 13 boxes. The collection is arranged into two (2) series. Series have been designated for: I. General Files of the Chief of Staff and Deputy Chief of Staff and; II. Cabinet Meeting Journal. These records include agreements, reports, correspondence, memorandums, budget documents, agendas, handouts, and invitations. This collection documents the actions of Governor Kaine's Chief of Staffs: William Leighty (2006-2007), Wayne Turnage (2007-2010) and Deputy Chief of Staff Stephen Harmes (2007-2010).
A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Counselor's Office, Records, 2001-2009 (bulk 2006-2009). The Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Executive Office-Counselor's Office, Records are housed in 33 boxes. The collection is arranged into five (5) series. Series have been designated for: I. General Files of the Counselor to the Governor; II. Judicial Appointments; III. Special Counsel Files; IV. Attorney General Settlements; and V. Files of Lawrence Roberts, Counselor and Shane Emmett, Legal Fellow. These records include agreements, reports, correspondence, e-mail, memorandums, legal briefs, legal files, budget documents, agendas, handouts, meeting notes, and invitations. This collection documents the actions of Governor Kaine's Counselor's Office. The majority of this collection is closed for 75 years per Code of Virginia, 2.2-3705.1 (attorney-client privilege).
A Guide to the Governor Timothy M. Kaine, Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Records, 2006-2009. The Senior Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Records of Governor Timothy M. Kaine are housed in 6 boxes. The collection is arranged into two (2) series. Series have been designated for: I. Correspondence; and II. Research Project Files. These records include correspondence, memorandums, notes, reports, presentations, contracts, decision briefs, plans, and project files. These records document the workforce development activities of the Kaine administration (2006-2010).
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Liaison Office, 2003-2010 (bulk 2006-2009). The Virginia Liaison Office records, 2003-2009 (bulk 2006-2009), are housed in 34 boxes. The collection includes series for Director's correspondence and subject files, Policy Analyst correspondence and subject files, National Governor's Association, and Southern Governor's Association.
CABINET OFFICES
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, 1995-2010 (bulk 2006-2009). Correspondence, reports, reviews, memorandums, decision briefs, legislative files and other working papers created and collected by the Office of the Secretary of Administration during the gubernatorial term of Virginia Governor Tim Kaine, 2006-2010. This collection consists of 13 records series which document the activities of the Office of the Secretary of Administration, as well as the agencies and boards which fall under its heading.
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, 2002-2010 (bulk 2005-2009. Records, 2002-2009 (bulk 2005-2009), created and maintained by Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry, Robert S. Bloxom, during the administration of Governor Timothy M. Kaine (2006-2010). The records include agendas, correspondence, memorandum, newspaper clippings, presentations, programs, reports, speeches, studies, and other working papers. Also included are incoming and outgoing correspondence with constituents and subject files of Deputy Director, William P. Dickinson.
A Guide to the Records of the Office of Commonwealth Preparedness, 1989-2009 (bulk 2006-2009). The Office of Commonwealth Preparedness records consist of 37 archival boxes and are divided into eight series. Series have been designated for Cabinet Meeting Files, Commonwealth Interoperability Coordinator's Office Initiatives Files, Commonwealth Interoperability Coordinator's Office Subject files, Constituent Correspondence, Correspondence and Supporting Documentation, Homeland Security Files Grant, Meeting Files Preparedness Committees, and Robert P. Crouch Jr. Attorney Files. These records document the work of the Office of Commonwealth Preparedness. The bulk of the records can be found in the Correspondence and Supporting Documentation series related to base closings, campus security, hurricane preparedness, interoperability, the National Capital Region, and various office projects. Included are agendas, correspondence, minutes, newsletters, programs, reports, and surveys. Of note are the Constituent Correspondence and Correspondence and Supporting Documentation series which are invaluable in showing the concerns and interests of citizens, government officials, and other individuals regarding security, terrorism, and various other subjects.
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Health and Human Resources, 2005-2010. Contains records created and maintained by Secretary of Health and Human Resources, Marilyn B. Tavenner, during the administration of Governor Timothy M. Kaine. The records include incoming and outgoing correspondence with assigned agencies and constituents, subject files, decision memoranda, legislative files, budget material, and records related to activities and special projects.
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Natural Resources, 1999-2010 (bulk 2006-2009). This collection contains the records, 1999-2010 (bulk 2006-2009), of the Office of Secretary of Natural Resources L. Preston Bryant, Jr., during the administration of Governor Tim Kaine. There is correspondence and subject files that relate to Secretary Bryant, the state agencies that he oversees, environmental organizations that operate in Virginia, and projects initiated by Governor Kaine. Legislative files contain material related to bills that were either under the purview of the Secretary of Natural Resources or upon which the Secretary wished to comment. Special programs include correspondence and subject files primarily created by Assistant Secretary of Natural Resources Missy Neff and Deputy Secretary of Natural Resources Nikki Rovner. Finally, there are speeches given by L. Preston Bryant, Jr., at public and private events.
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Public Safety, 1990, 1992, 1996, 1998-2010 (bulk 2002-2009). The Secretary of Public Safety records consists of thirty-eight archival boxes and are divided into six series. Series have been designated for Correspondence-Assigned State Agencies, Correspondence and Supporting Documentation-Office of the Secretary, Decision Memoranda and Briefs, Federal Grant Funding, Legislative Files, and Special Projects and Studies. These records document the activities of the Office of the Secretary of Public Safety, as well as the agencies and boards which fall under its heading, during the gubernatorial terms of Governor Mark R. Warner (2002-2006) and Governor Timothy M. Kaine (2006-2010).
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Technology, 2000-2009 (bulk 2006-2009). This collection contains the records, 2000-2009 (bulk 2006-2009), of the Virginia Secretary of Technology. Includes correspondence and subject files, which contain information on the inward-facing aspects of the Office of the Secretary of Technology. There are also special projects and studies which relate to health care, higher education, access to broadband internet, intellectual property, and interoperability. Legislative files contain information relating to bills of interest to the Secretary of Technology. Finally, there is material from the meetings of the Information Technology Investment Board.
A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, 2006-2010. The Secretary of Transportation records consist of 52 archival boxes and are divided into 4 series. Series have been designated for Appointment Calendars (I), Constituent Correspondence (II), Legislative Files (III) and Special Projects and Studies (IV). These records document the work of the Secretary of Transportation Pierce Homer during the Kaine administration and were created or collected, 2006-2009, though some documents in this collection pre-date this time period.
LIVE WEBSITES
The Virginia General Assembly's Legislative Information System contains searchable databases for bills and resolutions from 1994 to the present and reports to the general assembly. It also includes links to the Code of Virginia, Virginia Administrative Code, Constitution of Virginia, Charters, Authorities, Compacts and Uncodified Acts.
The Virginia Regulatory Town Hall website provides information about proposed changes to Virginia's regulations, including a meetings calendar and board minutes.
The Virginia State Budget Portal provides information about Budget Bills, Budget Amendments, and Committee Reports related to the budget from 1996 to the present.
The Virginia Department of Planning and Budget assists the Governor's Office, General Assembly, and state agencies develop and implement the budget. The website contains information on Virginia's budget from 2000 to the present.
Contents List
- I. Decision Briefs, 2005-2010 (accession 44690)., Extent: 2.10 cubic feet (6 boxes). (Box 1-6)
  The Decision Briefs series is housed in 6 boxes and is arranged alphabetically by cabinet secretary. Within each secretary, the records are filed in chronological order. The series consists of decision briefs, requests, recommendations, background information and supporting documents including correspondence and legislative citations.
  This series documents Governor Kaine's responses to requests from Executive Branch agencies for expenditure of funds from various sources controlled by the Governor's Office, approval of bond sales, letters from the Governor, and issuance of executive orders. Each Decision Brief usually includes: a description of the request including background material, discussion, and conclusions by the Policy Office; a recommendation from Richard D. Brown, Director, Department of Planning and Budget; and concurrence from Secretary of Finance Jody M. Wagner, the cabinet secretary overseeing requesting agency, and the Director of Policy (Brian Sheppard), Counselor to the Governor (Lawrence Roberts, 2006-2009 and Mark E. Rubin, 2009-2010) and Chief of Staff (William H. Leighty, 2006-2007 and Wayne Turnage, 2007-2010). If all concur, the Governor then signs the brief.
  Also included are referendums, disaster area requests to the Federal Government and requests for executive orders. 2009 Decision Briefs are not extant.
  - Governor Mark R. Warner Administration
    - November 2005 - January 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Secretary of Administration
    - Request for Emergency Capital Project for a Master Lease: Interstate Corporation Center (ICC) in Norfolk, Virginia, approved 2 May 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Department of General Services Request for a Deficit Loan in the Amount of $8.2 million, denied 18 August 2006 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Compensation Board Request for Transfer of Funds ($2.5 million) to Address Projected Shortfall re VRS Rate Increase, approved 28 April 2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Department of Charitable Gaming (DCG) Request for $90,000 for Implementation regarding HB 1998, approved 21 May 2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Comprehensive Agreement Between Department of Forensic Science and Sheer Partners Management, Inc., approved 19 July 2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Approval to Purchase 600 E. Main Street to Accommodate a Consolidated Department of Taxation Central Office, approved 21 July 2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Secretary of Agriculture and Forestry
    - Referendum on the Levy of an Excise Tax on Apples, 24 April 2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Referendum Authorizing an Increase on the Assessment of Cotton, approved 23 June 2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Referendum on Levy of an Assessment on Manufactured Equine Feed, approved 30 June 2006 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letter to U.S. Secretary of Agriculture Mike Johanns, Declaration of Disaster Area for Rappahannock and Pittsylvania Counties, 2 August 2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letter to U.S. Secretary of Agriculture Mike Johanns, Declaration of Disaster Area for Campbell County, 22 August 2006 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Executive Order Approval: EO for Declaration of State of Emergency to Assist Rockbridge County and Goshen due to a Critical Water Shortage (2007) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Federal Drought Declaration Request for Brunswick and Caroline Counties, 9 August 2007 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Federal Drought Declaration Request for Bedford, Bland, King George, Lancaster, Loudoun and Orange Counties, 13-14 August 2007 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Federal Drought Declaration Request for Essex, Northumberland and Warren Counties, 22 August 2007 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Federal Drought Declaration Request for Craig, Greensville, Halifax, Rappahannock and Surry Counties, 29 August 2007 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Federal Drought Declaration Request for Albemarle-Westmoreland Counties, 12 September 2007 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Federal Drought Declaration Request for Campbell-Tazewell Counties, 14 September 2007 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Executive Order 63, Declaration of a State of Emergency Arising from Heavy Winds and Brush Fires or the Potential thereof throughout the Commonwealth of Virginia (transmittal form only), March 2008 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Approval to Designate 26.627 Acres as Part of State Forest Managed by Department of Forestry, approved 17 September 2008 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Secretary of Commerce and Trade
    - Bond Package, Virginia Housing Development Authority (VHDA) Tax-Exempt Single-Family Housing Bonds ($800,000), approved 29 May 2006 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Virginia Economic Development Partnership $3 million transfer to Higher Education Research Initiative, approved 28 August 2006 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - BRAC Grant Program Design Vehicle to Provide Grant Funding, approved October 2006 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Virginia Small Business Financing Authority Transfer of $108,971,496 for Virginia Housing Development Authority (2006 carry forward), approved 29 December 2006 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Awarding of State's BRAC Grants, Round One, $12.5 million, approved 29 December 2006 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Virginia Housing Development Authority $1.3 million in Tax-Exempt Single Family Housing Bonds, approved 6 March 2007 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Governor's Approval of Virginia Small Business Financing Authority Bond Issue, approved 11 July 2007 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Virginia Employment Commission Closures, approved 27 March 2008 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Grant Transfers from the City of Hampton to the Fort Monroe Federal Area Development Authority, approved 2 June 2008 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Request for Executive Order, Private Activity Bonds: Delegation to the Director of Department of Housing and Community Development for Certification of Bond Allocation Caps, June 2008 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Authorization to Transfer $6 million to Secretary of Commerce and Trade for SRI-Shenandoah Valley, approved June 2008 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Recommended Approval of Grant Offer, 2008 Virginia Community Development Block Grants, approved 19 June 2008 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Grant to Virginia Beach concerning "Military Strategic Response Fund", approved 1 July 2008 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Recommended Approval of Grant Offer, 2008 CDBG Construction Ready Water and Sewer Fund Award, approved 21 July 2008 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Executive Order to Allocate Housing Bond Authority, Housing and Economic Recovery Act of 2008, approved October 2008 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Governor's Approval of Virginia Small Business Financing Authority Bond Issue (2), approved 13 January 2010 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Assistant to the Governor for Commonwealth Preparedness
    - Department of Homeland Security Grants, approved 30 August 2006 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Signing the National Capital Region Mutual Aid Agreement, approved December 2006 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - City of Virginia Beach Request for an Extension of their First BRAC Related Grant to 30 June 2008, approved 31 May 2007 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Awarding of the State's BRAC Grants, Round Two, approved 14 June 2007 (Box 2, Folder 3a)
  - Secretary of Education
    - Decision Brief - Whether to Continue to Use the Term "Governor's" as part of the "Governor's Early College Scholars Program", approved 16 February 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Request for Approval by State Board of Education to Apply for a $15,000 Grant from National Association of State Boards of Education, approved 2 May 2006 (Box 2, Folder 5)